Guide to the Lawrence H. Mamiya Papers, 1943-2006
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Lawrence H. Mamiya Papers
1943-2006
Mamiya, Lawrence H.
3.4 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Research files, survey data, oral history transcripts, photographic prints and academic writings by Lawrence Mamiya, documenting his research on the Nation of Islam and its role within African American communities and the Black church.
Biographical Note
Lawrence H. Mamiya (1942-2019) was born and raised in Hawaii and educated at the University of Hawaii (B.A. 1964), Union Theological Seminary (1964-1968), Graduate Theological Union (1968-1969), University of Konstanz (1972-1973), and Columbia University (Ph.D. 1975). From 1975 to 2014 he taught at Vassar College, where he served as chair of the Religion Department and director of the Africana Studies Program. In 1979 Mamiya launched the Green Haven Correctional Facility Program, Vassar’s first prison education program. His coursework prompted Vassar students to pursue careers in prison reform, social justice, and law. In addition, Mamiya worked as a community organizer in Harlem and a voting rights organizer for the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee in Georgia. A distinguished scholar of religion, Mamiya co-authored, with Dr. C. Eric Lincoln, The Black Church in the African American Experience (Duke University, 1990).
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes subject files documenting Lawrence Mamiya’s research and survey work assembled for The Black Church in the African American Experience. Subject files include profiles and survey data collected from African American Muslims in prison and individuals representing local church communities. Files also include oral history transcriptions from interviews held with masjid leaders and individuals in U.S.-based Islamic communities. Prominent among these transcriptions is one of a 1992 interview with Louis Farrakhan of the Nation of Islam. Writings files include academic manuscripts, articles and essays, as well as one thesis paper submitted to Mamiya in 2006 which includes correspondence and commentary from Dr. Mamiya. Two folders contain photographic prints, one of which documents an unidentified Muslim mosque and marketplace.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Vassar College Africana Studies Records
The Vassar College Biographical Files contains a file on Mamiya.
Subject Headings
Names:
Farrakhan, Louis
Organizations:
Green Haven Correctional Facility; Hartford Seminary; Vassar College
Subjects:
African American churches; Black Muslims; Education; Mosques as community centers; Mosques--United States; Prison educators
VCL Categories:
African Americans; Education; Religion; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, February 2022.
Acquisition Information
Gift of May Mamiya, 13 October 2021 (M2021-017).
Series List
- Series I. Subject Files, 1951-1998; (Box 1-4, 9)
  This series is arranged into two subseries, General and Survey Data. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically, as filed by the creator. Content includes raw data from Mamiya’s survey work documenting the role of spirituality within African American church communities and Islamic mosques based in the USA. Files include questionnaire templates and survey results, some including handwritten notations. Subject files related to survey work conducted by Lawrence Mamiya, Eric Lincoln and Ihsan Bagby contain data used in research assembled for the publication of The Black Church in the African-American Experience. Two folders in the series contain documentation on Vassar College’s Green Haven Prison Project.
- Series II. Oral History Transcriptions, 1992-1997; (Box 4-5)
  This series includes interviews held with African American men and women regarding the role of Islam, marriage, family life and spirituality within the African American community. One folder contains a transcript of an interview by Lawrence Mamiya and Eric Lincoln with Louis Farrakhan from 1992.
- Series III. Writings, 1968-2006; (Box 6-8, 9)
  This series contains academic manuscripts of Lawrence Mamiya addressing African American spirituality, the Black church experience, Islam in America, as well as a smaller volume of writings on the role of religion within prison life. One folder in the series contains a manuscript submitted to Mamiya in 2006 containing commentary and correspondence from Mamiya to the author.
- Series IV. Photographic Prints, 1943-1990; (Box 8, 9)
  This series consists of two folders of photographic prints contain black and white snapshots of an unidentified US-based Muslim mosque and marketplace, as well as color photocopies of the Islamic Society of America, dated 1943.
Container List
- SERIES I. SUBJECT FILES
  - General
    - African American Muslims in Prison, submitted to L. Mamiya by Thaufeer Al Deen, 1993 (Folder 1.1)
    - African American Muslim Women, essay by Aminah McCloud, 1993 Jan 1 (Folder 1.2)
    - Black Churches, printed materials, 1951-1981 (Folders 1.3-1.5)
    - Black Churches, rural profiles, [undated] (Folder 1.6)
    - Blackside Film and TV Productions, Atlanta Masjid of Al Islam, 1978-1999 (Folders 1.7-1.8)
    - Book reviews, Lawrence Mamiya publications, 1990-1992 (Folder 1.9)
    - Farrakhan, Louis, A Torchlight for America, book promotion, 1993 (Folder 1.10)
    - Farrakhan, Final Call, Schism in the Muslim Movement, 1979-1986 (Folder 1.11)
    - Financing African American Churches, with references to Mamiya research, 1998 (Folder 2.1)
    - Five Percent Nation of Islam, Smith, Cheryl Diane, 1984 May 1 (Folder 2.2)
    - Gallup Organization, Haves and Have Nots, Perceptions of Fairness and Opportunity, 1998 (Folder 2.3)
    - Gallup Organization, ITC Faith Factor Project, 2000 (Folder 2.4)
    - Green Haven Correctional Facility Prison Project, 1989-1992 (Folders 2.5-2.6)
    - Hartford Seminary, Advisory Group Meeting, 1980 (Folder 2.7)
    - International Islamic Conference, Islam in the New Century, Chicago, IL, 1998 Jun 1 (Folder 2.8)
    - Mount Ephraim Baptist Church, printed material, ephemera, 1997-1998 (Folder 2.9)
    - Muslims in prisons, questionnaire, 1991 (Folder 2.10)
    - Pacific and Asian American Center for Thought and Strategies, 1977 (Folder 3.1)
    - Parish profiles, Ousley United Methodist, Mt. Ephriam Baptist, New Horizons Church of God in Christ, 1999 (Folder 3.2)
    - Religion Colloquium, writings by Al-Ahari Bektashi, 1993 (Folder 3.3)
    - Saviours' Day, Nation of Islam, Chicago, IL, 1997 Feb 1 (Folder 3.4)
  - Surveys
    - Black Churches, Black Church in the Black Experience, survey results, circa 1980 (Folder 3.5)
    - Hartford Seminary, Islam in the African American Experience, Imam and Masjid Codebooks, Survey Results, raw data, circa 1980s (Folders 3.6-3.7)
    - Hartford Seminary, Qualitative coding questionnaire, African American Muslims, survey results and raw data, 1997 (Folders 3.8-3.7)
    - Islam in the African American Experience, Masjid members, Piety Scale, [undated] (Folder 4.1)
    - Islam in the African American Experience, survey results, with handwritten notations, 1998 (Folders 9.1-9.4)
    - Notes, Mamiya interviews, handwritten notations, 1994 (Folder 4.2)
- SERIES II. ORAL HISTORY TRANSCRIPTIONS
  - African American Women, Islam, Marriage, Family, 1 June 1996 (Folders 4.3-4.7)
  - Ihsan Bagby interview transcripts, 1993-1996 (Folders 4.8-4.10)
  - Ihsan Bagby interview transcripts, 1993-1996 (Folders 5.1-5.2)
  - Bagby/Mamiya interview transcripts, 1993-1996 (Folders 5.3-5.6)
  - Farrakhan interview with Dr. Eric Lincoln and Dr. Lawrence Mamiya, 1992 Oct 2 (Folder 5.7)
  - MSQ Imam interview, 1993-1997 (Folders 5.8-5.10)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - "Al Nisa: African American Muslim Women and Spirituality in Everyday Life,", [undated] (Folder 6.1)
  - "Between Black and White: The Asian in America,", 1977 (Folder 6.2)
  - "The Black Church in The Black Experience," Duke University, 1981 Nov 1 (Folder 6.3)
  - "The Black Church Through the Prism of Recent Social Science Research," Howard University, typed MS, 1982 (Folder 6.4)
  - "Black Militant and Separatist Movements,", 1986 (Folder 6.5)
  - "Black Muslims as a New Religious Movement," Chuo Academic Research Institute, 1987 (Folder 6.6)
  - "Black Muslims as a New Religious Movement: Their Evolution and Implications for the Study of Religion in a Pluralistic Society,", [undated] (Folder 6.7)
  - "Change and Continuity: Reformation and Reconstruction," with notations, 1993 (Folder 9.5)
  - "Class Differentiation in the African American Community and Its Implications for the Ministry of Black Churches,", 1989 Nov 1 (Folder 6.8)
  - "Daddy Jones and Father Divine," reprint, published in Religion in Life, 1980 (Folder 6.9)
  - "Ethnic Pluralism, Democracy, and the Black Church,", 1976 (Folder 6.10)
  - "Faith Based Institutions and Family Support Services Among African American Muslim Masjids and Black Churches,", [undated] (Folder 6.11)
  - "Faith Based Organizations and Ministry to High Risk Youths,", 2000 May 1 (Folder 6.12)
  - "For Their Courage and For Their Struggles," Poughkeepsie Black Oral History Project, 1978 (Folder 6.13)
  - "From Black Muslim to Bilalian: The Evolution of a Movement,", 1982 (Folder 6.14)
  - "Islam in America: Problems of Legacy, Identity, Cooperation and Conflict Among African American and Immigrant Muslims,", [undated] (Folder 6.15)
  - "Jailhouse Religion: Religion in Prison and Social Change in America,", [undated] (Folder 7.1)
  - Malcolm X, Elijah Muhammad, Minister Farrakhan, [undated] (Folder 7.2)
  - "Models of Secularization in Contemporary Sociological Theory,", 1972 (Folder 7.3)
  - "The Mourning After Los Angeles: Black Churches, Foundations and Urban Crisis,", 1992 Jun 1 (Folder 7.4)
  - "The Nation of Islam,", [undated] (Folder 7.5)
  - "The New Black Revolution: The Black Consciousness Movement and the Black Church,", 1990 (Folder 7.6)
  - "Policy and Planning Implications of the Christian Methodist Episcopal Church Survey,", undated (Folder 7.7)
  - "Psychedelic Drugs and Religious Experience, An Overview and a Critique..." Union Theological Seminary, typescript, 1968 (Folders 7.8-7.9)
  - "The Religion of Humanity in American Social Thought: Rational Religion and Reform," Columbia University, 1975 (Folder 7.10)
  - "River of Struggle, River of Freedom," Duke University, 2006 (Folder 7.11)
  - "The Second Episcopal District of the African Methodist Episcopal Church...,", 1986 (Folder 7.12)
  - SNCC, SIM, and the Southwest Georgia Project, 2011 (Folder 7.13)
  - "A Social History of the Bethel African Methodist Episcopal Church in Baltimore,", 1994 (Folder 7.14)
  - "Sociology, Morality and Religion: A Theoretical Reassessment of the Religion of Humanity Tradition,", 1977 (Folder 8.1)
  - "Transitions from Prison to Community," Casey Foundation Report, 2004 Feb 1 (Folder 8.2)
  - "Transitions from Prisons to Community, African American Muslim Mosques and Programs for the Formerly Incarcerated,", 2004 Feb 1 (Folders 8.3-8.5)
  - Untitled MS, History of African American Muslims, 2006 Dec 1 (Folders 8.6-8.8)
  - "You Never Hear About Their Struggles: Black Oral History in Poughkeepsie, NY,", 1980 (Folder 8.9)
  - "Finding the Sacred Behind the Wall, The Role of Religion in the Lives of Incarcerated Women," by Ilana Raskind, includes correspondence from L. Mamiya, 2006 (Folder 8.10)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHIC PRINTS
  - Snapshots, black-and-white, unidentified Muslim mosque, and marketplace, circa 1990 (Folder 8.11)
  - Photocopies, Islamic Society of America, 1943 (Folder 9.6)